<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[manzoidal meanderings]]></title>
  <link href="http://manzoid.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://manzoid.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-07T04:36:54-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://manzoid.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Tim Mansfield]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why do you want to learn how to code?]]></title>
    <link href="http://manzoid.com/blog/2013/08/04/why-do-you-want-to-learn-how-to-code/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-04T04:02:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://manzoid.com/blog/2013/08/04/why-do-you-want-to-learn-how-to-code</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have mentored quite a few people, over the years, in learning how to code. It&rsquo;s a happy hobby of mine. I&rsquo;ve been helped by many people over the years and I am glad to &ldquo;pay it forward&rdquo;, as they say.</p>

<p>But one glaring thing I have noticed is that people often can&rsquo;t really articulate <em>why</em> they want to learn to code. In itself, that&rsquo;d be fine, but <em>then</em>, usually just a few weeks or even a few <em>days</em> in, they crap out. They just plain, old-fashioned throw in the towel.</p>

<p>Despite a fair amount of encouragement, wheedling, cajoling, and prodding on my part, they just drift back to ogling <a href="http://geishaschooldropout.typepad.com/geisha_school_dropout/2013/04/signs-daenerys-targaryen-is-actually-asian.html">Daenerys Targaryen</a>, not having progressed much further along the path.</p>

<p>I feel that this comes about in part because we didn&rsquo;t really get to the bottom of what their real motivations were,</p>

<p>Now, I&rsquo;m not necessarily advocating doing some big &ldquo;couch session&rdquo; before simply diving in and doing stuff. Far from it. Just doing stuff is great! But at the same time, it&rsquo;s no surprise to anyone that learning to code well enough to actually do anything real is pretty hard. It&rsquo;s so hard that people quit in droves. So as partial inoculation against <em>chronic giveupitis</em>, I think it&rsquo;s a good idea to take a little time to sort through your motivations.</p>

<p>Being clearer about why you&rsquo;re doing something can help you stick with it. Biological organisms are generally inherently energy-conserving. If something really doesn&rsquo;t make sense to your brain, and you&rsquo;re just forcing yourself to do it anyway, some deep parts of you are going to say screwwwwww this… and trigger a hundred insidious rationalizations at the conscious level for giving up.</p>

<p>With that in mind, take a look at this laundry list that fell out of the top of my head just now. I&rsquo;m sure there are many more reasons than this that people could come up with, but hopefully some items in this initial list will resonate with you and help you articulate why you&rsquo;re in the game &mdash; and hopefully, by extension, why you&rsquo;re in it to win it!</p>

<ul>
<li>I want a job as a coder because it&rsquo;ll be a job…

<ul>
<li>that makes good money</li>
<li>with good future prospects</li>
<li>that&rsquo;s interesting</li>
<li>that&rsquo;s creative</li>
<li>that&rsquo;s exciting</li>
<li>where I work with smart, can-do people</li>
<li>that will let me work flexibly

<ul>
<li>part-time</li>
<li>remotely</li>
<li>from home</li>
<li>overseas</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>I want to build things

<ul>
<li>I like tinkering</li>
<li>I am curious about how things work</li>
<li>I like making things work</li>
<li>I want to leave a &ldquo;legacy&rdquo; of things I have built

<ul>
<li>even though software is ephemeral, still &mdash; to have made things…</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>I want to make an impact

<ul>
<li>I want to make things that improve people&rsquo;s lives</li>
<li>I want to become wealthy

<ul>
<li>and use that wealth to make an even bigger impact</li>
<li>and use the freedom I thereby gain, to make an even bigger impact</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>I want to start a company

<ul>
<li>I want the chance to make it big</li>
<li>I want to create a &ldquo;<a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/theyec/2012/09/21/7-reasons-most-people-should-build-lifestyle-businesses-not-startups/">lifestyle business</a>&rdquo; (in the <a href="http://jacksonfish.com/2009/03/13/lifestyle-business-defined-in-under-140-chars/">non-pejorative sense</a> of that term)</li>
<li>I want the challenge of wearing multiple hats</li>
<li>I want the challenge of growing a business</li>
<li>I want the excitement of responding quickly in the face of real market feedback</li>
<li>I want to provide jobs for others</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>I want more control / influence

<ul>
<li>I like being a &ldquo;power user&rdquo;</li>
<li>Knowledge is power; even as a non-programmer (a project manager, say), I&rsquo;ll have more ability to know what&rsquo;s going on and guide projects</li>
<li>I feel like software is everywhere, and if I can write it and modify it, I will be more powerful</li>
<li>I don&rsquo;t like feeling helpless; I want to be able to customize things to my liking</li>
<li>I want to be able to help others</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>I like games (or other app types)

<ul>
<li>I want to be able to make them myself</li>
<li>I want to write extensions for such apps</li>
<li>I want to be a useful and respected part of the community that does these things</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>I want to conquer my fears

<ul>
<li>I want to prove I can do it</li>
<li>I feel like a phony right now, and want to be more real</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>I like the intellectual challenge

<ul>
<li>I like puzzles</li>
<li>I like logic</li>
<li>I like systems and systems thinking</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>How about you?</h2>

<p>So… assuming you consider yourself to be a learner or at least a “Zen beginner’s mind” type of person still… does any of this resonate with you?</p>

<p>What floats your personal boat?</p>

<p>Anything to add to the list?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Parallel assignment in Ruby]]></title>
    <link href="http://manzoid.com/blog/2013/08/04/parallel-assignment-in-ruby/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-04T04:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://manzoid.com/blog/2013/08/04/parallel-assignment-in-ruby</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Parallel assignment</strong> is a handy feature of the Ruby language (a feature it shares with other languages, such as Python).</p>

<p>Parallel assignment is the way that Ruby handles multiple lvalues and/or multiple rvalues. <em>(Definitions: an &ldquo;lvalue&rdquo; is a value on the left-hand side of the equals sign, and an &ldquo;rvalue&rdquo; is a value on the right-hand side of the equals sign.)</em></p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s look at some concrete examples.</p>

<h3>Case #1: One value on the left, multiple values on the right</h3>

<p>The first, simplest case is when there is 1 lvalue and multiple rvalues. For example:</p>

<pre><code>&gt; a = 1, 2

&gt; a
 =&gt; [1, 2] 
</code></pre>

<p>All that&rsquo;s happening is the right-hand comma-separated list of values is converted into an array and assigned to the left-hand variable.</p>

<h3>Case #2: Multiple values on the left, the same number of values on the right</h3>

<p>The second case is when there are the same number of lvalues and rvalues. For example:</p>

<pre><code>&gt; a,b = 'foo', 'bar'

&gt; a
 =&gt; "foo" 
&gt; b
 =&gt; "bar" 
</code></pre>

<p>This is also pretty straightforward &mdash; you simply evaluate each item on the right hand, then assign it to its corresponding variable on the left-hand side, in order.</p>

<h3>Case #3: Multiple values on the left, one value on the right &mdash; but it&rsquo;s an array</h3>

<p>The third case is when the rvalue is an array, and that array&rsquo;s elements are distributed (or &ldquo;expanded&rdquo;) among multiple lvalues. For example:</p>

<pre><code>&gt; a, b = ['foo', 'bar']

&gt; a
 =&gt; "foo" 
&gt; b
 =&gt; "bar" 
</code></pre>

<p>This is effectively the same as case #2, above, except in this case explicitly employing array syntax.</p>

<h3>Case #4: More values on the left than on the right</h3>

<p>The fourth case is when there are multiple values on both sides, and there are more lvalues than rvalues. For example:</p>

<pre><code>&gt; a, b, c = 'foo', 'bar' # Note only 2 values on the right

&gt; a
 =&gt; 'foo'
&gt; b
 =&gt; 'bar'
&gt; c
 =&gt; nil 
</code></pre>

<p>As you can see, Ruby did the best it could to distribute the values, but ran out of them and was forced to assign <code>nil</code> to the last variable on the left.</p>

<h3>Case #5: More values on the right than on the left</h3>

<p>The fifth case is when there are multiple values on both sides, and there are fewer lvalues than rvalues. For example:</p>

<pre><code>&gt; a, b = 'foo', 'bar', 'baz' # Note only 2 values on the left

&gt; a
 =&gt; 'foo'
&gt; b
 =&gt; 'bar'
</code></pre>

<p>Again, Ruby did the best it could to distribute the values, but had too many to parcel out, and was forced to send the right-most value (&ldquo;baz&rdquo;) into the ether.</p>

<h3>Case #6+: Splatting</h3>

<p>Note in the case above, we lost the last value. However it is actually possible to capture any such excess values and gather them into an array, using a related operator called the &ldquo;splat&rdquo; operator (which consists of an asterisk in front of the variable, as in <code>*my_var</code>). You can do a number of useful things with this &ldquo;splat&rdquo; operator, but so as not to overload this post too much, it&rsquo;s probably better to go elsewhere to look at examples of it in action. E.g., <a href="http://endofline.wordpress.com/2011/01/21/the-strange-ruby-splat/">this other blog post</a> lists several variant uses. <br/></p>

<h3>Note: Swapping without a temp variable</h3>

<p>One nice aspect of this parallel assignment facility is that you can swap values conveniently.</p>

<p>To swap values <em>without</em> parallel assignment, you might write something like this:</p>

<pre><code>&gt; a = 'foo'
&gt; b = 'bar'
&gt; temp = a # Introduce a temp variable
&gt; a = b
&gt; b = temp

&gt; a
 =&gt; "bar" 
&gt; b
 =&gt; "foo" 
</code></pre>

<p>But with parallel assignment, you can simply rely on Ruby to implicitly handle the swapping for you:</p>

<pre><code>&gt; a = 'foo'
&gt; b = 'bar'
&gt; b, a = a, b

&gt; a
 =&gt; "bar" 
&gt; b
 =&gt; "foo"
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Money]]></title>
    <link href="http://manzoid.com/blog/2013/08/04/money/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-04T03:37:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://manzoid.com/blog/2013/08/04/money</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Everybody knows the truism that money doesn&rsquo;t buy happiness.</p>

<p>But is that true? Without money, it&rsquo;s pretty easy in America to wind up straight-up homeless &mdash; <a href="http://www.bygpub.com/books/tg2rw/chap1excerpt.htm">Marshall Brain will break that down for you, kids!</a> &mdash; and homelessness would seem to suck, leading to high stress and unhappiness, to put it mildly.</p>

<p>This is true despite a certain romanticization of the American hobo lifestyle a la <a href="http://www.woodyguthrie.org/biography/biography2.htm">Woody Guthrie</a>, the <a href="http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/297249.The_Boxcar_Children">Boxcar Children</a> series, and hipsters showing that they can <a href="http://qr.ae/Ik71A">pull it off for a little while</a>.</p>

<p>Admittedly, I was once pals with a dumpy, brilliant hacker back in the first Tech Bubble who lost every penny of a stupendous paper-fortune, became pretty depressed, and travelled around for the next couple years in a van. Perhaps he even parked it <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XaoM0FyLmGY">down by the river</a> at times. It turned out to be pretty good therapy, and the guy later came roaring back to a big role at Apple and make his fortune and find happiness after all, so maybe a stint of homelessness isn&rsquo;t all bad.</p>

<p>But these are exceptions that prove the rule. Bottom line is we need dough to get by, and figuring out how to acquire it does occupy a lot of our thought and effort.</p>

<p>Despite how hard most people work to earn a living, most people don&rsquo;t think of themselves as <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bjZRAvsZf1g">obsessed by money</a>. Most people are just trying to get by, and want a stable and hopefully semi-interesting job that helps them do that. Still, our minds are on our money, and money&rsquo;s on our minds.</p>

<h2>What is money, anyway?</h2>

<p>Personally I think of it in a straightforward way: <strong>money represents your desire and ability to have other people do something for you</strong>. If you can do it yourself, then you don&rsquo;t need to pay somebody else to do it, right?</p>

<p>Whether it&rsquo;s a product or service, it holds true. It&rsquo;s especially obvious when you hire a service &mdash; a person actually stands before you, doing something you hired them to do. But it&rsquo;s true when you buy an object as well.</p>

<p>It seems like you are buying a <strong>thing</strong>, but what you are really buying is the labor of the <strong>people</strong> who designed, built, packaged, transported, and sold that item for you, along with the cost of all the other people that <em>those</em> people paid to help them do those things.</p>

<p>This essential nature of money is obscured by the super-tangible-ness, the uber-concrete-ness of the product that you&rsquo;re buying. You&rsquo;re holding an iPhone, a cross-trainer sneaker, a block of sharp cheddar cheese, a sample bathroom tile &mdash; these things are very physical, and cost money. So that&rsquo;s what you&rsquo;re shelling out for, obviously &mdash; you&rsquo;re buying a thing, what could be more obvious?</p>

<p>But ultimately, that&rsquo;s not really what&rsquo;s going on &mdash; it&rsquo;s just the surface transaction, the trading of some paper bills for that physical product. However those products would not exist without human intervention. Italianate bathroom tiles do not grow on tile-trees. Even an orange, which does in fact grow on a tree, does not magically whisk its way to you, &ldquo;<a href="http://harrypotter.wikia.com/wiki/Summoning_Charm">Accio Orange</a>&rdquo;-style.</p>

<h2>But, but, but…!</h2>

<p><strong>&ldquo;But machines are making these things, not people!&rdquo;</strong> you might think to yourself.</p>

<p>But who&rsquo;s designing the machines? Who&rsquo;s operating them? Who maintains them when they break? Who makes sure to pay the bill for the juice they run on? Who organizes and manages all this effort? Whoever these people are, that&rsquo;s what you&rsquo;re really paying for, not for the operation of the machine. And you&rsquo;re also paying for all those other people who made the machines and sold them to the company making the product.</p>

<p><strong>&ldquo;What about real estate? Nobody&rsquo;s making that!&rdquo;</strong> you might think to yourself.</p>

<p>First, to be pedantic, that&rsquo;s actually not strictly true, sometimes <a href="http://japanpropertycentral.com/real-estate-faq/reclaimed-land-in-japan/">we do make land</a>. But in general, yes, humans don&rsquo;t create land. However, we humans do live in a cold universe for the most part, that doesn&rsquo;t recognize these little things we like to call &ldquo;rights&rdquo;.</p>

<p>What&rsquo;s to stop some dude from swinging by your place, shooting you and your family, or just beating you silly and throwing you out into the street, and taking your house? Well, the police, the court system, and ultimately the military, that&rsquo;s who. I.e., different levels of government make and enforce the complex system of property rights that prevent others from just killing you and taking your stuff.</p>

<p>When you fork over a cool $750,000 to buy a little house somewhere in Los Angeles, you are paying to influence 2 sets of people:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Explicit</strong>: The landowners, so they voluntarily give up their claim and publicly proclaim that you are the new owner.</li>
<li><strong>Implicit</strong>: The government and all its powerful instruments of violent persuasion, to make everybody respect that new claim, i.e., keep the forces of evil at bay and protect your property.</li>
</ul>


<p>So, it may sound strange, but I believe that the idea of property protection is actually built into the purchase price. I don&rsquo;t mean that there&rsquo;s some specific percentage of the purchase price that represents the human effort to protect your property (that&rsquo;s actually explicitly paid for elsewhere, in taxes that fund public services). Rather I mean that the fact that there is a price <em>at all</em> is indicative of the protection aspect.</p>

<h2>After the Apocalypse</h2>

<p>Consider a <a href="http://www.vertigocomics.com/graphic-novels/y-the-last-man-vol-1-unmanned">post-apocalyptic scenario</a>, where government had broken down, laws were unenforced, and people were desperate. Money would be basically worthless, right?</p>

<p>Why is that?</p>

<p>Well, it&rsquo;s because that proclamation that &ldquo;this guy I just sold this property to, he&rsquo;s the real owner&rdquo; &mdash; it would be worthless. It would be worthless because no powerful agents would enforce your property rights.</p>

<p>The belief that you really owned things because of an exchange of money would be severely weakened in an apocalyptic scenario. And why? Because <em>people</em> aren&rsquo;t protecting your rights.</p>

<p><strong>Everything comes down to what people are doing, or not doing, and who they&rsquo;re doing it for.</strong></p>

<p>This is what money really represents. I believe that understanding that is one of the keys to fulfillment in life.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll expand on this theme, in a more practical manner, in a future post.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
